[
    {
        "question": "Which companies were granted 'Navratna Status' by the central government?",
        "options": [
            "IRCTC and NTPC.",
            "IRFC and ONGC.",
            "IRCTC and IRFC.",
            "NTPC and ONGC."
        ],
        "answer": "IRCTC and IRFC."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the recipient of the Gangadhar National Award for Poetry 2023?",
        "options": [
            "Sitakant Mahapatra",
            "Prativa Satpathy",
            "Jayanta Mahapatra",
            "Ramakanta Rath",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which legendary cricketer was awarded honorary membership of the Melbourne Cricket Club (MCC)?",
        "options": [
            "Sunil Gavaskar",
            "Sachin Tendulkar",
            "Kapil Dev",
            "Sourav Ganguly"
        ],
        "answer": "Sachin Tendulkar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned the 'Spell Master of India' in SBI Life Spell Bee Season 14?",
        "options": [
            "Medhansh Vaddadi",
            "Yashwin Pachauri",
            "Chaya M V",
            "Mandira Bedi",
            "Sakshi Sinha"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which award will Taika Waititi receive at the 36th Producers Guild of America Awards?",
        "options": [
            "Academy Award",
            "Golden Globe Award",
            "Grammy Award",
            "Norman Lear Achievement Award",
            "Pen Pinter Prize"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were the key contributions of S. M. Krishna to Indian politics, and which prestigious award was he honored with in 2023?",
        "options": [
            "Transforming Bengaluru into India's Silicon Valley; Padma Shri",
            "Establishing Karnataka as a leading agricultural state; Bharat Ratna",
            "Advocating for women's empowerment and rural development; Padma Bhushan",
            "Serving as Chief Minister of Karnataka and Minister of External Affairs; Padma Vibhushan",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which prestigious award has Indian environmentalist Madhav Gadgil received in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Nobel Prize for Environmental Science",
            "UNEP's Lifetime Achievement Award",
            "Tyler Prize for Environmental Achievement",
            "Padma Bhushan",
            "Environment Engineer Award"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state was awarded the Geographical Indication (GI) tag for its traditional handicraft, 'Gharchola,' known for its intricate designs and cultural motifs?",
        "options": [
            "Rajasthan",
            "Gujarat",
            "Punjab",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Haryana"
        ],
        "answer": "Gujarat"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indian Film Personality of the Year at the 55th International Film Festival of India (IFFI)?",
        "options": [
            "Amitabh Bachchan",
            "Rajinikanth",
            "Vikrant Massey",
            "Nawazuddin Siddiqui",
            "Deepika Padukone"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned Miss India USA 2024 at the event held in New Jersey?",
        "options": [
            "Nirali Desia",
            "Manini Patel",
            "Sanskriti Sharma",
            "Caitlin Sandra Neil",
            "Shipra Negi"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indira Gandhi Prize for Peace, Disarmament, and Development 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Ban Ki-moon",
            "Angela Merkel",
            "Veronica Michelle Bachelet",
            "Jacinda Ardern",
            "Malala Yousafzai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who posthumously honored Dr. Vishakha Tripathi Ji with the Lifetime Achievement Award for her extraordinary service to humanity?",
        "options": [
            "World Health Organization (WHO)",
            "Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)",
            "United Nations Development Program (UNDP)",
            "Asia Pacific Vascular Society (APVS)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Jamsetji Tata Award for pioneering the biosciences movement in India?",
        "options": [
            "Ratan Tata",
            "Janak Kumar Mehta",
            "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw",
            "B Muthuraman",
            "Adar Poonawala"
        ],
        "answer": "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw"
    },
    {
        "question": "India received the ISSA Good Practice Award for Asia-Pacific 2024 for which purpose?",
        "options": [
            "Launching a nationwide pension scheme",
            "Enhancing agricultural productivity",
            "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)",
            "Advancing renewable energy technologies",
            "Developing multilingual education platforms"
        ],
        "answer": "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company won two awards at the 3rd PSU Transformation Awards 2024 for Innovative Product Development and Technology Adoption?",
        "options": [
            "Cochin Shipyard Limited",
            "Hindustan Shipyard Limited",
            "Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Limited",
            "Garden Reach Shipbuilders & Engineers",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Hindustan Shipyard Limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who will receive the Lifetime Achievement Award at the 77th Annual Directors Guild of America (DGA) Awards, and what makes their contributions significant?",
        "options": [
            "Steven Spielberg; known for his blockbuster films and innovative techniques",
            "Ang Lee; recognized for his diverse filmmaking and cinematic excellence",
            "Martin Scorsese; celebrated for his contribution to crime and drama genres",
            "Ridley Scott; honored for his work in science fiction and historical epics",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Which researcher from the Zoological Survey of India (ZSI) is credited with discovering the new species of pangolin, named the Indo-Burmese pangolin (Manis indoburmanica), in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Lenrik Konchok",
            "Suresh Naik",
            "Ramesh Pandey",
            "Deepa Sharma",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been named the ICC Men's ODI Cricketer of the Year 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Rashid Khan",
            "Azmatullah Omarzai",
            "Babar Azam",
            "Rohit Sharma",
            "Jasprit Bumrah"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the Dronacharya Award for outstanding coaches in Sports and Games 2024 in the Regular Category for Hockey?",
        "options": [
            "Shri Harendra Singh",
            "Shri Sandeep Sangwan",
            "Shri Randhir Singh Gentle",
            "Shri Harmik Singh",
            "Shri Yograj Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which university was honored with the prestigious MAKA Trophy 2024 and had a student, Sanjay Kumar, receive the Arjuna Award for hockey?",
        "options": [
            "Amity University",
            "Chandigarh University",
            "Banaras Hindu University",
            "Delhi University",
            "LPU"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which former Indian hockey player received the Padma Bhushan award on the eve of the 76th Republic Day?",
        "options": [
            "R Ashwin",
            "Inivalappil Mani Vijayan",
            "Harvinder Singh",
            "PR Sreejesh",
            "Manpreet Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "PR Sreejesh"
    },
    {
        "question": "Christine Carla Kangaloo, President of _________, was awarded the Pravasi Bharatiya Samman Award 2025.",
        "options": [
            "Guyana",
            "Trinidad and Tobago",
            "Fiji",
            "Mauritius",
            "Algeria"
        ],
        "answer": "Trinidad and Tobago"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the recipient of the Major Dhyan Chand Khel Ratna Award 2024 for his outstanding contribution to sports?",
        "options": [
            "Virat Kohli",
            "Neeraj Chopra",
            "Manika Batra",
            "Harmanpreet Singh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned the ICC Women's ODI Cricketer of the Year for 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Laura Wolvaardt",
            "Tammy Beaumont",
            "Hayley Matthews",
            "â€‹Smriti Mandhana",
            "None of the abocve"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the JC Daniel Award 2023 for lifetime contributions to Malayalam cinema, and what are some of his notable achievements?",
        "options": [
            "TV Chandran for pioneering new-wave cinema",
            "KS Chitra for contributions to music in Malayalam films",
            "Shaji N Karun for showcasing Malayalam cinema on the international stage",
            "Vijayaraghavan for his acting in Malayalam cinema",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Shaji N Karun for showcasing Malayalam cinema on the international stage"
    }
]